Nicole: The effects on business that
Covid19 has had, and the shift to
remote working has had a major impact
on the world of cyber security.
Remote working has for many involved
unplanned cloud migrations and the
purchase of new IT products and systems.
To get up to speed quickly companies have
bought off the shelf security systems
or have relied on a workers own security
system in their own homes which may
not be adequate or configured properly.
This has created new levels
of vulnerability and risk
across a range of industries.
Abraham: The success of remote
working has also meant that there
is now a shift towards making this
a more permanent feature for many.
Organisations will therefore need
to assess their current security
infrastructures and address any areas
of weakness that may have appeared
by developing a long-term remote
security strategy, going forward.
Ransomware is one of the most common
threats to an organisations cyber security
and this is increasing all the time.
The techniques used by criminals
are getting more sophisticated and
extortion attacks are on the increase.
This has a major economic impact
on organisations from not only the
cost of paying the ransom but also
the loss of revenue during any
disruption and the subsequent loss
of business and brand reputation.
Nicole: Traditionally in the past
companies were able to create
secure networks in their office
with a firewall perimeter around it.
This allowed them to then trust
access from that network to
sensitive corporate networks.
With most of the workforce now
working from home, this poses a
new challenge of how to ensure
that only authorised employees are
accessing potentially sensitive data.
Many IT departments rely on VPNs to access
their networks, but these are proving
inadequate against the threat of phishing
as cyber attacks are on the increase.
Zero-trust network access or ZTNA is a
new more secure option for controlling
remote access to sensitive data,
reducing the likelihood of an attack.
This involves using a default approach
of “trust nothing” and only allowing
access using several contextual
authentication metrics, such as the
device that’s being used to connect,
the time they’re connecting, the
location they’re connecting from,
and the behaviour of the user.
Abraham: Multi-factor authentication
or MFA can offer an additional
defence against data breaches
and malicious attacks, forcing
individuals to use two or more separate
devices to confirm their identity.
This often involves a one-time passcode
being sent to two or more devices.
This can also take the form of a physical
USB device that a person carries with
them [much like their actual house keys]
which they plug in to their computer to
prove that they are who they claim to be.
This works on the fact that whilst
it’s somewhat likely at any given
time that a criminal may have taken
your credentials, it’s extremely
unlikely that they will have both your
credentials and your second factor,
such as your phone or your USB key.
Nicole: I am sure we all are getting
used to having one-time passcodes
sent to our phones that we must
input into the verification process.
However, Microsoft has recently
urged users to move away from
phone-based MFA due to the weak
security in telephone networks and
the fact that SMS messages are not
encrypted giving access to attackers.
Companies should use more
secure MFA methods like Google
or Microsoft authenticators.
AI and machine learning are growing
in sophistication and capabilities.
AI is being used increasingly to build
automated security systems analysing large
quantities of data at a much faster pace.
This can offer an opportunity
for greater threat detection, but
this technology can also work both
ways, offering cyber criminals the
opportunity to automate their attacks.
Criminals are then able to take large
data sets of emails and passwords
found on the ‘dark web’ from previous
breaches, and then automatically run
these through all the websites they
want to try to hack, with the hope
that people use the same password and
email for several different sites.
Once one logs in successfully,
they can then change that password
and take over that account.
Abraham: Remote working has increased
the demand on cloud services however
they are still a prime target for attack.
Organisations need to be on top of
their game when it comes to checking
for vulnerabilities in their current
infrastructure, such as checking
for misconfigured cloud settings.
There have been a growing number of
high-profile cyber attacks on data
privacy and personally identifiable
information or PII records.
Data privacy is now becoming
more of an issue for all of us.